Register of the I. M. Andreev papers
Hoover Institution Archives
I. M. Andreev papers
1944-1998
2008C40
Hoover Institution Archives
1 microfilm reel (0.15 linear feet)
Correspondence, and speeches and writings, relating to the Russian Orthodox Church and to Russian émigré education.
Andreev, I. M. (Ivan Mikhaĭlovich), 1894-1976.
Access
The collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2008
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Location of Original Materials
Holy Trinity Orthodox Seminary, Jordanville, New York
Biographical Note
1894 March 14 Born, St. Petersburg, Russia
1912-1914 Studied at Sorbonne, Paris
1918 Graduated, Psikhonevropatologicheskii institut, St. Petersburg
1927-1932 Incarcerated in the Solovetskii concentration camp
1948 Author, Blagodatna-li sovietskaia tserkov'?
1950 Arrived in the U.S.
1950-1971 Professor, Holy Trinity Orthodox Seminary, Jordanville, NY
1951 Author, Kratkii obzor istorii russkoi tserkvi ot revoliutsii do nashikh dnei Author, O polozhenii pravoslavnoi tserkvi v Sovietskom soiuzie: katakombnaia Tserkov' v SSSR
1957 Author, O kharaktere nauchno-ateisticheskoi propagandy v Sovietskoi Rossii
1960 Author, Kratkii konspekt kursa po psikhologii
1965 Author, Pravoslavno-khristianskaia apologetika
1966 Author, Pravoslavno-khristianskoe nravstvennoe bogoslovie
1968 Author, Ocherki po istorii russkoi literatury XIX vieka
1976 December 30 Died, Jordanville, NY
Scope and Content of Collection
The I. M. Andreev papers contain the correspondence and some writings of Ivan Mikhaĭlovich Andreevskii (pen-name I. M. Andreev), a prominent writer. These papers reflect only a fragment of Andreevskii's activities and writings. Among his Speeches and Writings are writings on pedagogy and psychology, as well as catacomb Orthodox communities in the U.S.S.R.
Note that while materials are listed as Box/Folder instances, they all appear on the single microfilm reel.
Custodial History note
Detailed processing and preservation microfilming of these materials were made possible by a generous grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities and by matching funds from the Hoover Institution and the Holy Trinity Seminary. The grant also provided for depositing a microfilm copy in the Hoover Institution Archives. The original materials remain in the Holy Trinity Seminary Archives as its property. Any views, findings, conclusions or recommendations expressed in these materials do not necessarily represent those of the National Endowment for the Humanities.
Russkai͡a pravoslavnai͡a t͡serkovʹ.; Russians--United States.; Education--United States.
- Biographical File, 1978-1998, undated (Reel 1, Box-folder 1: 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Articles about Andreevskii, arranged chronologically.
- Correspondence, 1947-1972, undated
  Cards and letters, arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent.
  - General, 1950-1968, undated
    - Postcards, 1950-1972, undated (Box-folder 1: 2)
    - Unidentified, 1950-1968, undated (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - Alfer'ev, Evgenii E., undated (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - Averkii (Taushev), Archbishop, 1949-1969 (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - Gol'denveizer, Alexis, 1957 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - Grabbe, Georgii, Archpriest, 1952-1957 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - Grigor, Ioann, Archpriest, 1950 (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - Grinko, A., 1953 (Box-folder 1: 9)
  - Grotov, Sergei, 1962-1972, undated (Box-folder 1: 10)
  - Gusev-Orenburgskii, S., undated (Box-folder 1: 11)
  - Hunter, Holland, 1954 (Box-folder 1: 12)
  - Kanev, Victor, 1964 (Box-folder 1: 13)
    Includes Alyi Tsvetok, holograph.
  - Kashkina, Anna, 1951-1954 (Box-folder 1: 14)
  - Konstantinov, Dimitrii, Archpriest, 1966 (Box-folder 1: 15)
  - Kontsevich, Elena and Ivan, 1957-1968, undated (Box-folder 1: 16)
  - Losskii, Nikolai, 1952-1955, undated (Box-folder 1: 17)
  - Mel'nikova, Evdokima, 1950, undated (Box-folder 1: 18)
  - Nikon (Rklitskii), Bishop, 1960-1965 (Box-folder 1: 19)
  - Pol'skii, Mikhail, Archpriest, 1947-1960 (Box-folder 1: 20)
    Includes "Proekt. Ustav Korporatsii Praviashchago Arkhiepiskopa i eparkhial'nago soviet Sievero-Amerikanskoi i Kanadskoi eparkhii Russkoi Pravoslavnoi Tserkvi Zagranitsei."
  - Pomazanskii, Mikhail, Archpriest, 1960 (Box-folder 1: 21)
  - Rybinskii, N., 1954 (Box-folder 1: 22)
  - Serafim (Ivanov), Bishop, 1957 (Box-folder 1: 23)
  - Troitskii, N., 1966 (Box-folder 1: 24)
  - Sorokin, Pitirim, 1947 (Box-folder 1: 25)
  - Vitalii (Maksimenko), Archbishop, 1958 (Box-folder 1: 26)
- Speeches and Writings, 1947-1960, undated
  Drafts and printed copies of articles and writings, arranged chronologically and thereunder by title.
  - Untitled draft of a work on ecclesiastical history, parts I, II and VI, undated (Box-folder 1: 27)
    Typescript
  - "Khristianstvo kak osnova zhizni," (table of contents), undated (Box-folder 1: 28)
    Holograph
  - "O pravoslavno-khristianskom nravstvennom vospitanii dietei doshkol'nago vozrasta,", undated (Box-folder 1: 29)
    Printed copy. Includes undated typescript of foreword to second edition.
  - "Osnovy mirovozzreniia pravoslavnogo khristianina,", undated (Box-folder 1: 30)
  - "Russkoe pravoslavnoe bogosluzheniie kak kliuch k ponimaniiu khrama,", undated (Box-folder 1: 31)
  - Zamietki o katakombnoi tserkvi v SSSR, 1947 (Box-folder 1: 32)
    Printed copy
  - Nauchnoe znanie i khristianskaia istina, 1948 (Box-folder 1: 33)
  - "Molitva optinskikh startsev,", 1949 (Box-folder 1: 34)
    Photocopy of magazine article
  - Kratkii konspekt kursa lektsii po psikhologii, 1960 (Box-folder 1: 35)
- Writings by Others, 1948-1959, undated
  Arranged alphabetically by author.
  - Unidentified
    - "Khotielos'-by poniat',", undated (Box-folder 1: 36)
    - Notes (Box-folder 1: 37)
  - Leontii (Filipovich), Bishop, Averkii (Taushev), Bishop, Serafim (Svezhevskii), "Arkhiereiskomu soboru Russkoi Pravoslavnoi Tserkvi Zagranitsei v N'iu-Iortke. Dokladnaia zapiska,", 1959 (Box-folder 1: 38)
  - Popov, Aleksandr, "Proiskhozhdenie i osnovy russkoi monarkhicheskoi vlasti,", 1948 (Box-folder 1: 39)
  - Popowicz, Nikolaj P., "Das Neuburger Weiss, seine Natur und Entstehung,", 1951 (Box-folder 1: 40)
  - Trofinovich, Zoia, "Nekotorye iz osnovnykh motivov tvorchestva I. A. Bunina,", undated (Box-folder 1: 41)
- Rossiiskoe Monarkhicheskoe Ob"edinenie Zagranitsei File, 1948-1949, undated (Box-folder 1: 42)
  Includes issues of Vestnik otdela russkogo monarkhicheskogo ob"edineniia, 1948-1949, and "Ustav Rossiiskogo monarkhicheskogo ob"edineniia zagranitsei," undated. Arranged chronologically.
- Photographs, 1944-1957
  - Two prints of Andreevskii, 1950-1957 (Box-folder 1: 43)
  - One print of Bishop Ioasaf (Skorodumov), 1944 (Box-folder 1: 44)